Guide to the Woolsey Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Printed Materials, Miscellaneous Writings, and Photographs, 1754-1936; Series IV; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Yale
    - Connecticut, State of, Legislation concerning Yale Medical Department, 1789 (Box 53, Folder 54)
    - Acts of the General Assembly concerning Yale, 1878 (Box 53, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous, 1847, 1851, 1857, 1867, 1870, undated (Box 53, Folder 55)
  - Photographs
    - of Theodore Dwight Woolsey, 1860, undated (Box 53, Folder 56)
    - relating to William Dunlap, 1914, 1918, undated (Box 53, Folder 57)
    - Miscellaneous, 1903,undated (Box 53, Folder 58)
    - of Edward E. Salisbury, undated (Box 53, Folder 59)
- Genealogical Records, 1873-1913; Series V; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This series contains correspondence, notes, printed matter, charts, and abstracts of articles pertaining to the genealogy of the Woolsey family. The series also includes Family Memorials, (1885), a printed genealogical record of Elizabeth Martha (Salisbury) Woolsey by Edward Elbridge Salisbury.
  - Articles, Abstracts and Charts, undated (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Source Materials, undated (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1873-1913 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Printed materials, 1874, 1875, 1897, undated (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Index Rerum, by John Todd, D.D., Undated (Box 54A)
  - Family Memorials, the genealogical record of Elizabeth Martha (Salisbury) Woolsey (printed), by Edward Elbridge Salisbury, 1885 (Box 55, Folder 6)
- Family Business Documents, 1693-1923; Series VI; 1.75 linear feet (5 boxes)
  The Family Business Documents are divided into two sub-sections, "Business Papers," which are arranged chronologically, and "Bound Ledgers and Account Books," which are alphabetically arranged. Most of the latter section pertains to the personal finances, house-hold accounts, bank statements, and accounts for children of Theodore Dwight Woolsey.
  - Business Papers
    - Family Business, 1780, 1784, 1787-1788, 1794, 1800, 1802, 1806, 1825, 1830-1831, 1836, 1812-1813, 1832-1834 (Jun) 1834, July-December 1835-1836, 1838-1843, 1840-1843 (Box 56, Folder 1-8)
    - Family Business, 1844-1849, undated, 1850-1857 (Box 57, Folder 9-20)
    - Family Business, 1858-1872, 1874, 1876, 1878, 1880, 1886, 1889-1890, 1918, 1923, undated (Box 58, Folder 21-32)
  - Ledgers and Account Books
    - Accounts, 1693-1703, of a general store in Jamaica, L.I., kept by Capt. George Woolsey (52 pp.), continued 1740-1757, by his grandson Melancthon Taylor Woolsey (pp. 53-83), followed by personal accounts, 1759, 1766-1770, of the latter's wife, Rebecca (Lloyd) Woolsey (Box 59, Folder 32a)
    - Unidentified volume, 1768-1772 (Box 59, Folder 32b)
    - Unidentified miscellaneous household expense notebooks, 1855 (Box 59, Folder 33)
    - TDW, accounts for children; inheritance of TSW, 1873-1881 (Box 59, Folder 34)
    - TDW, City Bank of New Haven accounts, 1853-1862, 1876-1886 (Box 59, Folder 35)
    - TDW, general accounts, 1861-1879 (Box 59, Folder 36)
    - TDW, household accounts, 1834-1864 (Box 60, Folder 37)
    - TDW, household accounts, accounts for children, 1844-1861 (Box 60, Folder 38)
    - TSW, Corn Exchange Bank, check book stubs, 1910-1911 (Box 60, Folder 39)
- William Walton Woolsey Estate, 1838-1869; Series VII; 2.25 linear feet (6 boxes)
  The records of the WILLIAM WALTON WOOLSEY ESTATE consist of journals, ledgers, general accounts, and legal papers pertaining to the disposition of the estate of William Walton Woolsey. Also included in this series are the records of Ohio land sales, 1838-1878, which formed an important part of the Woolsey estate. The executors of the estate, John Mumford Woolsey, Theodore Dwight Woolsey, and Samuel Johnson administered the trusts created by his will for the benefit of his widow, children, and others.
  The series is divided into three subsections: "Accounts," "Land Sales," and "Ledgers" Folders are arranged alphabetically by title within each section.
  - Accounts
    - Corrections on Executor's Books, undated (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Executor's Copies of accounts (Inventory), 1840-1859 (Box 61, Folder 2)
    - Executor's copies of accounts, 1862-1867, 1863 (Box 61, Folder 3-4)
    - Executor's accounts, 1841-1867 (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Executor's drafts of Journals and Ledgers, 1861-1866 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Executor's Index to Vouchers, 1842-1865 (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - Executors of estate, Mr. Kyte's Report, 1839-1858 (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Mary Anne (Woolsey) Hoadley, 1840-1861 (Box 61, Folder 9)
    - Sarah Dwight (Woolsey) Johnson, Fund Account, 1839-1867 (Box 61, Folder 10)
    - Sarah Dwight (Woolsey) Johnson, Income Account, 1840-1867 (Box 61, Folder 11)
    - William Samuel Johnsoln, Executor of WWW Estate, 1842-1860 (Box 62, Folder 12)
    - Merchant's Bank, 1839-1860 (Box 62, Folder 13)
    - Merchant's Bank, William C Woolsey, agent, 1839-1840 (Box 62, Folder 14)
    - Elizabeth (Woolsey) Winthrop, 1862-1863 (Box 62, Folder 15)
    - Sarah Chauncey Woolsey, Annuity Fund, 1839-1859 (Box 62, Folder 16)
    - Sarah Chauncey Woolsey, Annuity Fund, Mr. Kyte's Report, 1839-1859 (Box 62, Folder 17)
  - Assignment of Mortgage and Declaration of Trust, 1839-1840 (Box 62, Folder 18)
  - Journal: No. 1, 1839-1860 (Box 62, Folder 19)
  - Journal: No. 2, 1861-1869 (Box 62, Folder 20)
  - Journal, 1839-1867 (Box 63, Folder 21)
  - Journals, 1842-1862 (Box 63, Folder 22)
  - Law Suit: Elizabeth W. Winthrop, et al va. W.W. Woolsey Estate, 1864-1867 (Box 63, Folder 23)
  - Law Suit: John M. Woolsey, et al v. Administrator of Richard C: McCormic, 1841-1855 (Box 63, Folder 24)
  - Ledgers: No. 1, 1839-1860 (Box 63, Folder 25)
  - Ledgers: No. 2, 1862-1869 (Box 63, Folder 26)
  - Ledgers, 1861-1863 (Box 63, Folder 27)
  - Ledger, 1839-1863 (Box 64, Folder 28)
  - Land Sales
    - Case lots, 1844-1860 (Box 64, Folder 29)
    - Cleveland lots, 1838-1859 (Box 64, Folder 30)
    - Collections from, 1844-1862 (Box 64, Folder 31)
    - Disbursements for, 1842-1862 (Box 64, Folder 32)
    - Mr. Kyte's Report, undated (Box 64, Folder 33)
    - Maps of lots, 1863 (Box 64, Folder 34)
    - Ohio Estate, 1835-1855 (Box 64, Folder 35)
    - Special Accounts and Inventories, 1839-1860 (Box 64, Folder 36)
    - Waste Book, 1852-1878 (Box 64, Folder 37)
  - Ledgers
    - WWW, business letters, 1833-1839 (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - WWW, cash expense accounts, 1832-1838 (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - WWW, Merchants' Bank checkbook with account stubs, 1836-1839 (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - WWW and George Griswold, Trustee's Accounts, 1826-1833 (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - WWW and George Griswold, notebook, 1826-1833 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Legal case book, Dunlap, T. A, attorney, 1819-1824 (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - Legal case book, Johnson, Samuel, 1822-1828 (Box 66, Folder 7)
- William Walton Woolsey Business Papers, 1762-1839; Series VIII; 11 linear feet (27 boxes)
  This series consists of the business correspondence of William Walton Woolsey, two folders of the correspondence of Nicholas Bayard, some legal documents, and a number of letters and documents pertaining to the Manumission Society and the Chamber of Commerce of New York City. The entire series has been arranged chronologically.
  - WWW and Chamber of Commerce of New York, 1787-1789, 1791-1799 (Box 67, Folder 1-4)
  - WWW and Nicholas Bayard, 1762, 1769, 1773, 1784, 1785, 1790-1791, 1793-1794, 1796-1799, 1802-1803, 1805 (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - Business Correspondence, 1795-1805 January-July (Box 68, Folder 7-14)
  - Business Correspondence, 1805 July-Dec, 1806-1808 (Box 69, Folder 15-29)
  - Business Correspondence, 1809 January-August (Box 70, Folder 30-37)
  - Business Correspondence, 1809 September-December (Box 71, Folder 38-43)
  - Business Correspondence, 1809, month undated, 1810 January-April (Box 71, Folder 44-49)
  - Business Correspondence, 1810 May-Dec, 1810, month undated (Box 72, Folder 50-63)
  - Business Correspondence, 1811 January-Dec, 1811?, 1812-1813, 1813? (Box 73, Folder 64-81)
  - Business Correspondence, 1814, January-June 29, 1814 July-December (Box 74, Folder 82-102)
  - Business Correspondence, 1815, January-December (Box 75, Folder 103-121)
  - Business Correspondence, 1816, January-Dec, 1816? (Box 76, Folder 122-147)
  - Business Correspondence, 1817-1818, January-August (Box 77, Folder 148-172)
  - Business Correspondence, 1818, September-Dec, 1819, January-July (Box 78, Folder 173-197)
  - Business Correspondence, 1819, August-Dec, 1820, January-August (Box 79, Folder 198-216)
  - Business Correspondence, 1820, September-Dec, 1820?, 1821, January-March (Box 80, Folder 217-232)
  - Business Correspondence, 1821, April-December (Box 81, Folder 234-243)
  - Business Correspondence, 1822, January-Dec, 1823, January-June (Box 82, Folder 244-263)
  - Business Correspondence, 1823, July-Dec, 1824, January-July (Box 83, Folder 264-279)
  - Business Correspondence, 1824, August-Dec, 1824, 1824?, 1825, January-August (Box 84, Folder 280-294)
  - Business Correspondence, 1825, September-December, 1825?, 1826, January-December (Box 85, Folder 295-306)
  - Business Correspondence, 1827, January-Dec, 1828, January-August 15 (Box 86, Folder 307-319)
  - Business Correspondence, 1828, August 16-Dec, 1828?, 1829, January-Dec, 1829, 1829? (Box 87, Folder 320-334)
  - Business Correspondence, 1830, January-Jun, September-Dec, 1831, January-Dec, 1832, January-July (Box 88, Folder 335-351)
  - Business Correspondence, 1832, August-Dec, 1832, 1833, January-Dec, 1833 (Box 89, Folder 352-366)
  - Business Correspondence, 1834, January-Dec, 1834?, 1835, January-Dec, 1836 (Box 90, Folder 367-377)
  - Business Correspondence, 1837, January-December, 1838, January-Oct, 1836, November-December (Box 91, Folder 378-389)
  - Business Correspondence, 1839, January-Aug, undated (A-Z), undated and unsigned (Box 92, Folder 390-396)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 93, Folder 390-396)
    - Leather pouch (Box 93, Folder 397)
    - Letter cover stamped 'Dr G T McMaster' (Box 93, Folder 398)
    - Lock of "Dear Mattie's Hair Dec 8th 1870" (Box 93, Folder 399)
    - Map of Alaska, hand-drawn (Box 93, Folder 400)
    - notes (Box 93, Folder 401)
    - Signet, "Manus Haec Inimica Tyrannis" (Box 93, Folder 402)
    - Silk Bookmark (Box 93, Folder 403)
- Theodore Dwight Woolsey Other Papers, 1846-1869; Series IX; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series consists of three parts: materials concerning the American Education Society, reports of committees attending term examinations, and gradebooks.
  - American Education Society
    - Letters of recommendation for student aid
      - 1847 - 1869, undated (Box 94, Folder 1-4)
    - Appropriations for student aid, 1846-1863 (Box 94, Folder 5)
    - Receipts for appropriations, 1849-1868 (Box 94, Folder 6)
  - Reports of committees attending term examinations, 1847-1865 (Box 94, Folder 7)
  - Gradebooks
    - 1846 - 1856 (Box 94, Folder 8)
    - 1849 - 1857, undated (Box 94, Folder 9)
    - undated (Box 94, Folder 10)
  - ALS from Leonard Bacon to Theodore D. Woolsey on printed catalogue of the professors and students of Andover Theological Seminary, 1821 April 12, 17 (Box 95)
  - Academic and honorary degrees, miscellaneous certificates
    - William Walton Woolsey, 1799 (Box 95)
    - Theodore Dwight Woolsey, 1827-1886 (Box 95)
    - Theodore Salisbury Woolsey, 1894, 1903 (Box 95)
    - George Meissner and Charles Upham Shepard, 1867 (Box 95)
- Additional material, 1800s-1950s; Accession 1988-M-081; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1989 Dec
  Received from: Anne La Farge, 1988 Apr 20
  - Correspondence of Laura Woolsey Heermance, 1881-1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of Laura Woolsey Heermance, 1908-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of Laura Woolsey Heermance, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of Laura Woolsey Heermance, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence of Laura Woolsey Heermance, 1951, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence of Laura Woolsey Heermance, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence of Agnes Woolsey, 1863-1867, 1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence of others, 1883, 1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Appointment books of L.W. Heermance, 1897, 1928, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travel journals of L.W. Heermance, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passport of L.W. Heermance, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of friends and family of L.W. Heermance, 1894, 1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Bryn Mahr classmates, 1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorabilia, 1899, 1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Postcard collection, 1920, 1928-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Albums of pressed flowers, 1870, 1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified family photographs, travel scenes, 1916, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Additional material, 1855, 1862; Accession 1996-M-086
  - Letter from Theodore Dwight Woolsey to his daughter, Agnes Woolsey, concerning her proposed trip abroad, 1855 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Journal of a Year of European Travel in 1856-1857," by Agnes Woolsey [two illustrated volumes, second edition], 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Additional material, 1870, undated; Accession 2005-M-070
  - Family genealogy [Heermance-Woolsey family], Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Heermance, Agnes Woolsey, travel journals, vols. I-II, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Additional material, 1976; Accession 2009-M-011
  - Woolsey, Robert M. The Woolsey Family: A Genealogy in the form of Annotated Family Charts, 1939-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Contains genealogical records from the fifteenth century to the 1970s. The main work of compilation was done in 1939-1969, with revisions made through 1976.
  - Woolsey, Robert M. The Woolsey Family: A Genealogy in the form of Annotated Familyl Charts, 1939-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 1808-1868; Accession 2015-M-032
  These materials came to Yale after being separated from the Johnson Family Papers retained by the Stratford Historical Society. The bulk of this accession documents the estates of the Woolsey family and their individual and joint business and realty endeavors.
  While the Woolsey and Johnson families were connected in a multitude of ways, a major connecting thread in this accession is William Samuel Johnson, Yale Hon. MA 1819, husband to Laura Woolsey, who was a lawyer and co-executor of William Walton Woolsey's estate with Theodore Dwight Woolsey and John M. Woolsey. A substantial portion of this accession documents William Samuel Johnson's legal career, including a manuscript establishing William Samuel Johnson's law partnership with Seth Staples, founder of the Yale Law School.
  Researchers will also find several dozen letters to John Mumford Woolsey from his sister, Sarah Dwight (Woolsey) Johnson, wife of Charles Frederick Johnson (a cousin of William Samuel Johnson), regarding family and financial matters, including her personal estate, of which John was a trustee. One letter discusses career plans for her son, William Woolsey Johnson, Yale 1862, who became a distinguished mathematician (1868 May 8). Sarah's investing acumen is evident in a telegram sent in June 1868 at the height of the great transcontinental railroad race, reading "Buy Central Pacific if possible."
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1823-1863 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dutton, Henry
      - Cannon, Philip A., 1838-1844 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hoadley, George, 1825-1827 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Johnson, William Samuel, 1833-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - McCormick, Richard, 1824-1856 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Waters, George G., Circa 1854-1863 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Woolsey, John M.
      - General, 1847, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Johnson, Sarah Dwight, Circa 1863-1869 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Woolsey, William C., 1839 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Woolsey, William Walton, 1813-1839 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Account registers, Circa 1839-1865 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Attorney appointments, 1832-1846 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Checks and promissory notes, Circa 1810-1863 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Johnson, Sarah D. estate, Circa 1842-1869 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Johnson, William Samuel
    - Accounting and legal practice, Circa 1808-1865 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Agreements, Circa 1829-1860 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Paid notes, obligations and bonds, 1825-1856 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Promissory notes, 1832-1869 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Receipts, 1841-1859 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Joralemon, Nicholas N., Circa 1836-1857 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Land sales, 1840-1847 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Leases, 1833-1849 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mortgages, Circa 1829-1858 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Receipts
    - General, Circa 1837-1847 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Rent and building repair, 1823-1847 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Woolsey family, Circa 1839-1843 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Staples, Seth, 1825-1827 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Taxes, 1846-1849 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Tenant's agreements, 1844-1851 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - William W. Woolsey and George Griswold vs. William C. Holly and Others, Circa 1825-1831 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Theodore D. Woolsey et al. vs. John M. Woolsey et al., 1860 January 6 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Woolsey, Catherine R. estate, 1843-1858 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Woolsey, John M. - Ohio land deeds, 1834-1852 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Woolsey, William Walton
    - Estate, 1823, 1833-1847 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ohio land sale contracts, 1845-1862 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)